<?xml version="1.0"?>
<main>
	<title>HOWTO: Write a Disk Image to USB Media on FreeBSD</title>
	<body>
<article>

  <header>
    <h1>HOWTO: Write a Disk Image to USB Media on FreeBSD</h1>
    <p><time datetime="2021-05-11T16:30:07+00:00">May 11, 2021</time></p>
  </header>

  <p>This HOWTO will describe the process of writing a disk image to USB media using only tools available in all FreeBSD installations. I wrote this using FreeBSD 13.0 but the command line tools and options should work on older versions.</p>

  <p>A disk image will usually end with <code data-nocopy="true">.img</code> or <code data-nocopy="true">.iso</code>. A <code data-nocopy="true">.iso</code> can usually either be written to USB media or to a CD/DVD.</p>

  <p>This document will assume the reader has a very basic understanding of the command line.</p>

  <h1 id="steps">Steps</h1>

<ol>
  <li>Insert the USB drive into the USB port. If using other media, insert the media into the reader/writer and insert that into the USB port.</li>
  <li>
    <p>Open a terminal and run <code>geom disk list</code> to view all attached disks. You should be able to identify it by the size of the disk (“mediasize”) and the manufacturer’s name (“descr”).</p>

    <p>Sample output of <code>geom disk list</code>:</p>

    <pre data-nocopy="true">Geom name: da0
Providers:
1. Name: da0
   Mediasize: 8166703104 (7.6G)
   Sectorsize: 512
   Mode: r0w0e0
   descr: Verbatim micro USB
   ident: 11122488000854
   rotationrate: unknown
   fwsectors: 63
   fwheads: 255</pre>

<p>The name is what we need. Here that’s <code data-nocopy="true">da0</code>, but for the remainder of this document I’ll refer to it as <code data-nocopy="true"><em>XXX</em></code> to prevent copy/paste accidents.</p>
  </li>
  <li>Run <code>su</code> to switch to root.</li>
  <li>
    <p>Run the following command.</p>

    <div class="warning">
  <h2>WARNING</h2>

  This command is destructive. The disk’s data will be entirely overwritten and it will be impossible to retrieve. Only proceed if you’re sure you’re using the correct disk.
</div>

<pre>cat myfile.img /dev/zero | dd of=/dev/<em>XXX</em> bs=1M</pre>

<p>This command will write <code data-nocopy="true">myfile.img</code> to the <code data-nocopy="true"><em>XXX</em></code> disk, and then continue to write zeros to the disk until the disk is full.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h1 id="notes">Notes</h1>

<p>It’s important to write zeros to the remainder of the disk as sometimes old data can be interpreted as part of the disk image.</p>

<p>The <code data-nocopy="true">bs=1M</code> flag is necessary because writing a disk byte-by-byte is extremely slow. Writing a disk in 1 mebibyte blocks (1MiB = 1 mebibyte = 1024² bytes) will be significantly faster in most cases. The ideal block size flag to pass will differ depending on the hardware used, but <code data-nocopy="true">1M</code> will work well enough. (<a href="https://serverfault.com/questions/650086/does-the-bs-option-in-dd-really-improve-the-speed">More about the <code data-nocopy="true">bs</code> flag</a>)</p>
</article>
	</body>
</main>
